Guide to the Food Studies Ephemera Collection MSS.310
Fales Library and Special Collections
Food Studies Ephemera Collection
1900-2015
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fales Library
MSS.310
7.75 Linear Feet in 18 boxes, 2 folders in a shared manuscript box and 1 folder in a shared flat box.
The Food Studies Ephemera Collection consists of pamphlets, recipe booklets, and other food- and cookery-related ephemera donated to Fales by various donors.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Accruals
Further accruals are anticipated.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials gifted by various donors from 2011 to 2019. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2011.310, 2014.412, 2015.310, 2018.094, and 2019.051.
Arrangement
The Collection is arranged alphabetically by subject, followed by subsequent accretion entries.
Custodial History
The items in the Food Studies Ephemera Collection have been donated to NYU by a number of individuals from the general public.
Scope and Contents
The Food Studies Ephemera Collection consists of printed ephemera (primarily pamphlets and recipe booklets) having to do with food and cookery. The bulk of the materials are from the mid-twentieth century.
Menus.; Cooking, American -- History -- 20th century.; Printed ephemera.; Pamphlets.; Food industry and trade -- United States.; Recipes.; Food science and technology.; Calendars.; Cuisinart (Firm)
- Ac'cent, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Advertisements, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- American Weekly, The, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Articles, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Artificial Sweeteners, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Auction Books, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Aunt Jemima's, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Australian, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Automobiles, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Avocados, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Baking Powder, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Baking Soda, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Bananas, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Beans, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Beard, James A., undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Beef, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Betty Crocker (1 of 2), undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Betty Crocker (2 of 2), undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Bisquick, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Blake, Mary, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Blank, Fritz, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Blenders, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Blue Ribbon, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Booksellers, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Borden, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Breads, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Buffalo, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Bulk Cooking, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Calendars- European Gastronomy (1 of 2), undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Calendars- European Gastronomy (2 of 2), undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Calendars- Florida, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Calendars- James Beard, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Calendars- Martha Stewart, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Calendars-Sopexa, undated (Box "Acc-Cal")
- Calendars- Weight Watchers, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Calendars- Wine, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- California, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Campbell's, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Camping, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Candy, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Canned Foods, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Canned Meats, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Canning, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Carnation, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Casserole, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Catalogues (1 of 4), undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Catalogues (2 of 4), undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Catalogues (3 of 4), undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Catalogues (4 of 4), undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Cheese, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Chef Pamphlets, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Child, Julia, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Children, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Chinese, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Citrus, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Cocktails, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Cocoa and Chocolate, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Coffee, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Cookies, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Cooking Schools (Home Ec.), undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Cookware, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Corn Syrup, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Cornell Rural School Leaflet, undated (Box "Cal - Cor")
- Cotton Oil, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Cranberries, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Cream Cheese, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Cuisinart Food Processor, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Culinary Arts Institute, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Culinary Historians of NY, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Daily Food Guide, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Dairy, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Danish, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Desserts, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Diet, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Diners (Folder 1)
- Doughnuts, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Dried Fruits, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Duncan Hines, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Eastern European, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Eggs, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Evaporated Milk, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Exhibitions, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Family, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Farmer, Fannie, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Fish, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Fleischmann's, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Florent, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Florida, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Flour, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Foley, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Food Arts, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Food Conferences, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Food Science, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Freezing, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- French, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- French's, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Fruit, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Game Meat, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Gardening, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Garlic, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Garnish, undated (Box "Cot - Gar")
- Gas Stoves, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Gelatine, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- General Electric, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Georgia, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Girl Scouts, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Gourmet, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Grains and Cereals, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Greece, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Hawaii, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Hebrew (1 of 2), undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Hebrew (2 of 2), undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Heinz, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Helpful Hints, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Herbs, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Holiday, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Honey, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Household Management, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Housewares, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Hovis, Gene, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Hungarian, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Indian, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Invitations, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Italian, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Japanese, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Jell-O, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Jewish, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Junior Chef Real Food Toys, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Kellogg, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Kellogg/ Battle Creek Sanitarium, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Kikoman, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Kiwis, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Kraft Foods, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Lamb, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Lipton, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Liquers, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Mango, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Margarine, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Marion Nestle Soda Politics: Taking on Big Soda (And Winning) Book Tour, 1995 (Flat-file-folder 14 Right)
- Mayonnaise, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Mazola, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Meat, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Medicine, undated (Box "Gas - Med")
- Menus, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Menu Planners, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Metropolitan (Met) Life, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Mexican, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Microwave, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Middle Eastern, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Miscellaneous Electric and Gas Housewares, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Molasses, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Moosewood Cookbook, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Mushrooms, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Nabisco, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Nestle's, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- NYC Food Museum, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- NYPL Culinary Collection, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Nutrition, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Nuts, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Olives, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Olive Oil (1 of 2), undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Olive Oil (2 of 2), undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Outdoor Cooking, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pam, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pächter, Mina, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Party Service, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pasta, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Peanut Butter, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pecans, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Soda, undated (Flat-file-folder 13 Right, Flat-file-folder 14 Right)
- Pet Food, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pickling, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pillsbury (1 of 3), undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pillsbury (2 of 3), undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pillsbury (3 of 3), undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pimentos, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pomegranate, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Popcorn, undated (Box "Men - Pop")
- Pork, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Port, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Post, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Potatoes, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Poultry, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Pressure Cookers, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Prosciutto, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Puerto Rican, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Quaker Oats, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Quiches, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Raisins, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Rangers, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Redbook, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Refrigerators, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Restaurant Guides (1 of 2), undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Restaurant Guides (2 of 2), undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Reynolds, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Russian, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Sauerkraut, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Scandinavian, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Schwartz, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Sea Food, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Sealtest (1 of 4), undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Sealtest (2 of 4), undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Sealtest (3 of 4), undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Sealtest (4 of 4), undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Sherry, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Shortening, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Snack Food, undated (Box "Por - Sna")
- Soup, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Sour Cream, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Southern African Rock Lobster, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Southern (1 of 2), undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Southern (2 of 2), undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Southwestern, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Spanish, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Spices (1 of 2), undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Spices (2 of 2), undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Substitutions, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Sunflower Oil, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Supermarkets, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Sweetener, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Taylor, Mary Lee (1 of 2), undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Taylor, Mary Lee (2 of 2), undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Taylor Wine Company, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Television, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Tunisian, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Turkish, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Union Square Cafe, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- USDA (1 of 2), undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- USDA (2 of 2), undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Vegan, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Vegetarian, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Vinegar, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Vitamins, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Vodka, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- WOR Gourmet Club, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Wartime, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Welch's, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Wesson, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Wheat Germ, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Wine, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Wish-Bone, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Woman's Home Companion, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Worcestershire, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Yeast, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- Zulu, undated (Box "Sou - Zul")
- 2015 Accretion: Cards and Postcards (Box 10, Folder 1)
- 2015 Accretion: Programs (Box 10, Folder 2-4)
- 2019 Accretion: Promotional Recipe Books, Pamphlets, Calendars, and Cruise Line Menu, 1953-1999, undated; .25 Linear Feet in 2 file folders in a shared manuscript box and 1 folder in a shared flat box. (Box Shared Fales 025, Folder 5-6, Box Shared Fales 009, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents
  This accretion includes recipe booklets and calendars, a French cruise liner menu from 1953, and information booklet on the food of Denmark from 1962. The recipe booklets were primarily published as promotional material by companies including Oklahoma Peanut and Pecan Commissions, Oklahoma Natural Gas Company, Giroux Grenadine Syrup, and California Raisin Advisory Board. The recipe books typically contain special recipes for products such has raisins or pecans, alcohol, or for specific holidays like Christmas. This accretion also has recipe books produced by Jim Loyd's Open Line and Family Favorites, which appears to have been a radio show. The calendars are also promotional items with recipes, sponsored by the Farmers' Almanac, Argo and Kingsford, and Cuisinart, dating from the late 1970s to the 1990s.
- Oversize - African, undated (Box 9)
- Oversize - Menus, undated (Box 9)
- Oversize - Society of Restaurateurs (photo), 1940 (Box 9)
- Unprocessed Accretion 2018.094
  - Marion Nestle book tour banner, 2016-04-13 (Box Shared Fales 032)